<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8' standalone='no'?>
<doxygen xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:noNamespaceSchemaLocation="compound.xsd" version="1.9.8" xml:lang="en-US">
  <compounddef id="nft" kind="page">
    <compoundname>nft</compoundname>
    <title>Nondeterministic Finite Transducers (NFTs)</title>
    <briefdescription>
    </briefdescription>
    <detaileddescription>
<para><simplesect kind="warning"><para>Mata provides an experimental (unstable) support for (non-)deterministic finite transducers (NFTs). The provided interface may change.</para>
</simplesect>
</para>
<sect1 id="nft_1nft_design">
<title>The design of NFTs in Mata</title>
<para>In Mata, the classical transducers from textbook definitions (where a transition is a tuple of <computeroutput>(initial state, input symbol, final state, output string)</computeroutput>) are encoded using a simpler data structure for the transition relation, <computeroutput><ref refid="namespacemata_1_1nft_1a7d4198ab11320a2e080b1fe3006a1179" kindref="member">mata::nft::Delta</ref></computeroutput> The data structures can directly represent only transitions of the form <computeroutput>p -a-&gt; s</computeroutput> where <computeroutput>a</computeroutput> is a single symbol or epsilon. A “high-level” transitions of the form <computeroutput>p -abc/def-&gt; q</computeroutput> where &apos;abc&apos; is an input word and def is an output word are encoded as a sequence of these &apos;low level&apos; transitions: <lsquo/>p -a- p’ -d-&gt; q -b-&gt; q<rsquo/> -e-&gt; r -c-&gt; r&apos; -f-&gt; s<lsquo/> (odd transitions read letters of the input track, even transitions read letters of the output track, a transition can have epsilon instead of a letter). The primed states are a sort of internal states, to where the automaton gets after reading a letter on the input tape. States are distinguished by their “level”. “Normal” states p,q,r,s have level 0, the internal states p’,q’,r’ have in this case the levels 1 (and you could have n-tape transducers where level can be larger than 1). In Mata, the <computeroutput><ref refid="namespacemata_1_1nft_1a7d4198ab11320a2e080b1fe3006a1179" kindref="member">mata::nft::Delta</ref></computeroutput> interface is used only for the manual handling of the internal delta representation, taking only (initial state, input symbol, final state) We find it useful to think about NFTs in Mata as normal NFAs with a single symbol on a transition (because Mata uses the same underlying data structure for NFTs as for NFAs) where states are annotated with levels. The &apos;NFT<rsquo/> states are the states with levels 0, the other levels are for the internal states. Each NFT transition is a sequence of NFA transitions, one per tape, between two states with levels 0. Each NFA transition performs a single symbol read on the tape of the source state. A sequence of symbols on transitions is not a single word on any tape, but an interleaved description of a single NFT transition over multiple tapes, e.g., q1(l:0)-{a}-&gt;q2(l:1)-{b}-&gt;q3(l:2)-{c}-&gt;q4(l:0) (where (l:X) describes the level of the state) is a single &apos;NFT&apos; transition (from a state with level 0 to another state with level 0) where the NFT symbol read is a 3-tape symbol (&apos;a&apos;, &apos;b&apos;, &apos;c&apos;), interpreted as &apos;read &apos;a&apos; on tape 0, read &apos;b&apos; on tape 1, and read &apos;c&apos; on tape 2.&apos; When you want to read &apos;af&apos; on a single tape, you need to construct two such transitions where on the remaining tapes, you read an epsilon symbol.</para>
</sect1>
<sect1 id="nft_1nft_usage">
<title>Working with NFTs</title>
<para>There are some utility functions to simplify creating this NFA-like Delta data structure for NFTs such as <computeroutput><ref refid="classmata_1_1nft_1_1Nft_1a1eb56e3967c0132d2b5be257f26a93d1" kindref="member">mata::nft::Nft::insert_word()</ref></computeroutput> (inserting the NFA-like sequence of transitions on different tapes: &apos;abcd&apos; which means to read &apos;ac&apos; on tape 0 and &apos;bd&apos; on tape 1), and <computeroutput><ref refid="classmata_1_1nft_1_1Nft_1a8989094f934980f8ac5792dc07d9cf6c" kindref="member">mata::nft::Nft::insert_word_by_parts()</ref></computeroutput> (inserting word for each tape separately: {&apos;ac&apos;, &apos;bd&apos;} to achieve the same as in the previous). If you however want precise control over the created transitions, you can omit using the utility NFT functions and build your NFT like an NFA using the Nft::Delta::* operations directly, adding a single symbol on a single tape per add() call. You will have to correctly specify the levels for the states. When working with 2-tape NFTs modelling a replace operation, we use <computeroutput><ref refid="namespacemata_1_1applications_1_1strings_1_1replace" kindref="compound">mata::applications::strings::replace</ref></computeroutput> namespace with utility functions such as <computeroutput><ref refid="namespacemata_1_1applications_1_1strings_1_1replace_1ad75bbee9ce1a38a91224e97a7c666ebd" kindref="member">mata::applications::strings::replace::replace_reluctant_regex()</ref></computeroutput> (accepting parameters: regex as the input for the tape 0, and a word as a replacement on tape 1), etc. The notion of jumps (in the jump mode RepeatSymbol, a mode designed for NFTs) is just an optimization to reduce the size of the NFT. It is an approach to simplify the data structure for NFTs where you can say that you jump over several internal states and NFA-like transitions to up to the next state with level 0, each transition in the sequence reading the same single symbol of the jump. That is useful when, for example, having a NFT reading string &apos;abc&apos; on all tapes. You can encode it as a sequence of jumps between states with level 0 as q0(l:0)-{a}-&gt;q1(l:0)-{b}-&gt;q2(l:0)-{c}-&gt;q3(l:0). Notice that the internal states are not present, but they are implied by the jump. Ideally, one should not even have to think about the levels and the intermediate states when properly using the utility functions (from the <computeroutput><ref refid="classmata_1_1nft_1_1Nft" kindref="compound">mata::nft::Nft</ref></computeroutput> class and the <computeroutput><ref refid="namespacemata_1_1nft" kindref="compound">mata::nft</ref></computeroutput> namespace in general).</para>
<para><simplesect kind="see"><para>examples/nft.cc example.</para>
</simplesect>
<simplesect kind="note"><para>If you find some expected NFT operation or utility function missing, do not hesitate to let us know and we will implement it. The interface for NFTs is not stable yet, so we are open to any and all feedback. </para>
</simplesect>
</para>
</sect1>
    </detaileddescription>
    <location file="/home/misa/Dokumenty/Nfa/mata/include/mata/nft/nft.hh"/>
  </compounddef>
</doxygen>
